Draper Corporation Glass Plate Negatives 6612 GPN
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Draper Corporation Glass Plate Negatives
1865-1927
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Draper Corporation
6612 GPN
54.25 cubic feet
54.2 linear ft.
Records (documents).
Photographs of Draper Company machinery, company events, company owned buildings, and surroundings.
10059736
Biographical / Historical
The Draper Corporation was once the largest maker of power looms for the textile industry in the United States. It operated in Hopedale, Massachusetts for more than 130 years.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of two series: Series A, 5 inch by 7 inch glass plate negatives, approximately 1,500; and Series B, 8 inch by 10 inch glass plate negatives, approximately 2,000.
Many of the photographs in Series A depict company outings, or "Field Days." These events were most likely organized by the Draper Company and may have consisted entirely of Draper Company employees. Founders of the Draper Company, brothers George and Ebenezer Draper were responsible for creating an integrated, planned community with innovative employee housing and recreational spaces, in addition to employment.
Series B consists largely of machinery built by the Draper Company. Also included are photographs of the company plant, employee housing, recreational facilities, and the surrounding area.
All negatives in this collection have been printed, please see collection 6612 P: Draper Corporation Photographs. Of the roughly 3,500 negatives 513 have been described at the individual level. Those descriptions are available in the container lists for both this collection and collection 6612 P.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 6612 G: Draper Corporation Graphics 6612 P: Draper Corporation Photographs 6612 PUBS: Draper Corporation Publications
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives 227 Ives Hall Tower Road Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheelref@cornell.edu https://catherwood.library.cornell.edu/kheel/
Compiled by:
R. Miles, December 19, 2017
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, December 22, 2017
Arrangement
Series A: 5 x 7 inch negatives.
Series B: 8 x 10 inch negatives.
Business records; Carding; Cloth bindings (Bookbinding); Cotton fabrics; Cotton manufacture -- Rhode Island -- West Warwick; Cotton manufacture -- Rhode Island -- Fiskeville; Cotton technology, General; Financial records; Local elections; Manufacturers' agents; Stores, Retail -- Rhode Island -- Richmond; Textile industry -- Rhode Island -- Richmond; Weaving -- Rhode Island -- Richmond; Wool industry -- Technological innovations; Woolen and worsted manufacture -- Rhode Island -- Richmond; Duxbury (Mass.) -- History -- 19th century; Industries -- Rhode Island -- Fiskeville; Massachusetts -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950; Industries -- Rhode Island -- Richmond; Industries -- Rhode Island -- West Warwick; Bucklin, E. C.; Bucklin, H. C.; Arkwright Mills, Inc.; Bookcloth Salesmen's Association; Draper Corporation; Harris Manufacturing Company; Harris Mill (Harrisville, N.H.); People's Reform Party (Mass.); Republican Party (Mass.)
10059736
- Series A: 5 x 7 inch negatives.
  - Temple Shop, Draper Company (Box 1, Folder 994)
    Scope and Contents
    Negative no.A994. 1891-1895. Image depicts a view of the Temple Shop at the Draper Company in Hopedale, Massachusetts The view shows a counter along the windows on the right and machinery, including lathes, on the left. A temple is a device on a loom located near the fell of the cloth, one on each side; temples hold the cloth out as wide as possible during the process of weaving and prevent it from being drawn in too much by the filling. See Negative 1000, in this box, for a view of the Temple Shop with a dozen employees and taken from the opposite angle as this one. The Temple Shop was built in 1868 for W. W. Dutcher. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. See box 4, folder 1065 for a very similar shot. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 5, Item 994 for print of this negative.
  - Hopedale Street: view from Draper Company office steps (Box 1, Folder 995)
    Negative no.A995. 1891-1895. Image depicts wooden residential buildings across an unpaved street from the office building. A man is riding a bicycle along the street. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. Original photograph by the Draper Company. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 5, Item 995 for print of this negative.
  - View looking down Adin Street (Box 1, Folder 996)
    Negative no.A996. 1891-1895. Image depicts a view looking down Adin Street in Hopedale, Massachusetts The street is unpaved but is lined with sidewalks and trees on both sides. The street curves to the left in the distance, and part of a clapboard building can be seen beyond the curve. Original photograph by the Draper Company. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 5, Item 996 for print of this negative.
  - Eben S. Draper House, Adin Street (Box 1, Folder 997)
    Negative no.A997. 1891-1895. Image depicts a view of Adin Street in Hopedale, Massachusetts Adin Street is unpaved but has paved sidewalks. In the center background is the Eben S. Draper House, built in 1885 by architect George T. Clarke of Boston. The house is three stories with multiple gables. Another house is to the left, further in the background. Eben Sumner Draper (1858-1914) was a leading figure in what later became the Draper Corporation, and served as the governor of Massachusetts between 1909 and 1911. Original photograph by the Draper Company. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 5, Item 997 for print of this negative.
  - Adin Street (Box 1, Folder 998)
    Negative no.A998. 1891-1895. Image depicts a view of Adin Street at the corner of another, unnamed street in Hopedale, Massachusetts Both streets are unpaved, but the far corner has a sidewalk and several stone steps leading up the house glimpsed behind the trees. The amount of space around the house suggests this was a upper-class neighborhood. Original photograph by the Draper Company. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 5, Item 998 for print of this negative.
  - Drafting Room, Draper Company (Box 1, Folder 999)
    Negative no.A999. 1891-1895. Image depicts a view of the Drafting Room at the Draper Company in Hopedale, Massachusetts Four male employees are visible; three sitting at drafting tables, and one leaning against a cabinet of drawers in the rear. Two framed prints hang on the wall in the rear with others propped up on the cabinet of drawers. The man seated on the left is dressed in a three-piece suit and wears a hat; he also holds a shuttle in his hands. The man leaning in the back also wears a three-piece suit and a hat. The man second to the left wears a vest but not a suit jacket; the man on the right wears a three-piece suit. Although taken from the same angle as seen in Box 3, Negative 1051, the arrangement of furniture is different, and this photo was probably taken at a different time. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 5, Item 999 for print of this negative.
  - Temple Shop men, Draper Company (Box 1, Folder 1000)
    Negative no.A1000. 1891-1895. Image depicts the male employees of the Temple Shop at the Draper Company in Hopedale, Massachusetts A dozen men, some in work clothes, and two in suits, stand in the Temple Shop, among equipment including lathes. A temple is a device on a loom located near the fell of the cloth, one on each side; temples hold the cloth out as wide as possible during the process of weaving and prevent it from being drawn in too much by the filling. See Negative 994, in this box, for a view of the Temple Shop without employees and taken from the opposite angle as this one. The Temple Shop was built in 1868 for W. W. Dutcher, a three-story brick factory on Social Street. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 5, Item 1000 for print of this negative.
  - Office building, Draper Company (Box 1, Folder 1001)
    Negative no.A1001. 1891-1895. Image depicts a two-story building designed in 1880 by architect Fred Swasey of Milford. A few men are standing on the porch entryway, barely visible under the overhang of the entryway roof. In the background are two smokestacks and partial views of a mill building and residences. Social Street runs in front of the building. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 5, Item 1001 for print of this negative.
  - Hopedale Pond (Box 1, Folder 1002)
    Negative no.A1002. 1891-1895. Image depicts a view of Hopedale Pond in Hopedale, Massachusetts, at ground level. Bushes line the pond in the foreground; some algae can be seen on the water. Trees line the pond in the background. See Box 2, Negative 1019 for a much better overall picture of the pond. Original photograph by the Draper Company. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 5, Item 1002 for print of this negative.
  - Chimney construction, Draper Company (Box 1, Folder 1003)
    Negative no.A1003. 1891-1895. Image depicts workers standing at the top of a scaffolded chimney that stands more than twice the height of three-story mill buildings to the left and right. The chimney extends through the roof of a one or two-story building in the center. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. Very similar to Negative 1004, in this box. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 5, Item 1003 for print of this negative.
  - Chimney construction, Draper Company (Box 1, Folder 1004)
    Negative no.A1004. 1891-1895. Image depicts workers standing at the top of a scaffolded chimney that stands more than twice the height of three-story mill buildings to the left and right. The chimney extends through the roof of a one or two-story building in the center. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 5, Item 1004 for print of this negative.
  - Northrop battery, Draper Co. (Box 1, Folder 1005)
    Negative no.A1005. 1891-1895. Image depicts a Northrop battery attached to a loom manufactured by Kilburn, Lincoln & Co. A battery is a mechanism found on single box automatic looms. The battery holds a plentiful supply of filling bobbins and transfers them, one at a time, to the shuttle as the need arises. A shuttle has been placed on the cloth being woven on the loom. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms including the Northrop loom. Kilburn, Lincoln & Co. was based in Fall River. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 5, Item 1005 for print of this negative.
  - G. M. Burgess House, Adin Street (Box 1, Folder 1006)
    Negative no.A1006. 1891-1895. Image depicts a two-story wooden residence with an attic and two chimneys. The home has a front porch and upper- and lower-story bay windows at the left side. Laundry hangs on clothesline on the far left. Other homes are partially in view. A front lawn reaches to the curbstone on Adin Street, which is unpaved. George M. Burgess was employed by Draper and had at least two patents to his name for improvements in textile machinery. Original photograph by the Draper Company. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 5, Item 1006 for print of this negative.
  - Loom with Northrup Battery, Draper Company (Box 1, Folder 1007)
    Negative no.A1007. 1891-1895. Image depicts a man in suit and tie examining a loom equipped with a Northrup battery. Note the box of bobbins on the left; this may be a broader view of the battery seen in Negative 1005, in this box. The man is unknown but is probably someone in management. The loom was photographed in front of a sheet, probably in an unknown mill. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 5, Item 1007 for print of this negative.
  - Hopedale, Massachusetts: aerial view from Draper Co. chimney, looking southeast (Box 1, Folder 1008)
    Negative no.A1008. 1891-1895. Image shows an aerial view of part of Hopedale, Massachusetts, taken from the (top of the) chimney of the Draper Company. The Bancroft house is at the bottom (presumably Joseph Bancroft's house--Bancroft was George Draper's brother-in-law); the Adin Ballou house is at the center left (Ballou was the founder of the Hopedale Community in 1842); and George Draper's house is at the center along Hopedale Street. Other residences, business buildings, and churches line neighboring town streets, but no part of the Draper Company complex is visible. Original photograph by the Draper Company. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 5, Item 1008 for print of this negative.
  - Pattern shop, Draper Co. (Box 1, Folder 1009)
    Negative no.A1009. 1891-1895. Image depicts the pattern shop at Draper Company. Here is where wooden patterns of gears and parts would be made before the parts would be manufactured in metal form. Six male workers are visible, standing around the shop. A saw is visible halfway down the aisle on the left. Several tables are laid out in a line down the room and carpenters' tools can be seen on the shelves in the right background. The Pattern Shop was located in a three-story brick building on Social Street, on the west side of Mill River. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. See Box 2, Negative 1027 for another view of this room with some of the same employees. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 5, Item 1009 for print of this negative.
  - Hopedale, Massachusetts: aerial view from Draper Co. chimney, looking northeast (Box 1, Folder 1011)
    Negative no.A1011. 1891-1895. Image depicts an aerial view of part of Hopedale, Massachusetts, taken from (the top of) the chimney of the Draper Company. A [Draper Co.?] boarding house and the Hopedale Elastic Fabric Company are at center left on Dutcher St. at Freedom St., built in 1887. Other residential buildings are scattered around, although most of the area is open fields. It is unclear exactly which building is the Hopedale Elastic Fabric Company as all of the buildings appear to be residential, unless it is the partial building seen on the left. Original photograph by the Draper Company. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 5, Item 1011 for print of this negative.
  - Hopedale, Massachusetts: aerial view from Draper Co. chimney looking east (Box 1, Folder 1012)
    Negative no.A1012. 1891-1895. Image depicts an aerial view of part of Hopedale, Massachusetts, taken from (the top of) the chimney of the Draper Company. Image shows houses on Dutcher Street. The three houses in the center (in front of the grove of trees) appear to be worker housing, as the two single-families on the right and the two-family on the left appear identical in style. Other houses can be seen further in the distance. See also another view of houses on Dutcher Street in Negative 1013, in this box. Original photograph by the Draper Company. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 5, Item 1012 for print of this negative.
  - Hopedale, Massachusetts: aerial view from Draper Co. chimney looking east, houses on Dutcher Street (Box 1, Folder 1013)
    Negative no.A1013. 1891-1895. Image depicts an aerial view of part of Hopedale, Massachusetts, taken from (the top of) the chimney of the Draper Company. Image shows houses on Dutcher Street, but from a different angle than that seen in Negative 1012, in this box. A number of the houses have free-standing clotheslines in them with laundry. The dark-colored, three-and-a-half story house on the left may be a boardinghouse, as it has a fire escape on the side. These houses were probably constructed for employees of the Draper Company. Wooded land behind the houses but a very large house can be glimpsed in the center background. Original photograph by the Draper Company. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 5, Item 1013 for print of this negative.
  - Draper Company: No. 3 automatic screw machine (Box 2, Folder 1016)
    Negative no.A1016. 1891-1895. Image depicts a view of the No. 3 automatic screw machine. Photographed in front of a white sheet, possibly in an unknown textile mill. See Negative 1017, in this box, for a view of this machine showing the toothed wheel. Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms, and apparently manufactured its own machine screws for use in its machinery. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 5, Item 1016 for print of this negative.
  - Draper Company: No. 3 automatic screw machine showing toothed wheel (Box 2, Folder 1017)
    Negative no.A1017. 1891-1895. Image depicts a No. 3 automatic screw machine showing a large toothed wheel in front; the toothed wheel is what would cut the grooves in the screws. Photographed in front of a white sheet, possibly in an unknown textile mill. See Negative 1016, in this box, for a view of the other side of this machine. Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms, and apparently manufactured its own machine screws for use in its machinery. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 5, Item 1017 for print of this negative.
  - Hopedale, Massachusetts: looking east from Draper Company machine screw shop (Box 2, Folder 1018)
    Negative no.A1018. 1891-1895. Image depicts a view from presumably the roof of the Draper Company's machine screw shop, showing single- and multi-family homes lining town streets near the company. Most of these residences were probably for Draper Company employees. The foreground view looks down onto a roof with three skylights and a number of vent pipes, probably part of the machine screw shop. Original photograph by the Draper Company. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 5, Item 1018 for print of this negative.
  - Hopedale Pond looking north from Freedom Street (Box 2, Folder 1019)
    Negative no.A1019. 1891-1895. Image depicts a view of Hopedale Pond looking north from Freedom Street. View taken from Draper Company shop, probably from the roof, as the view is quite high. One house on the left in the foreground; another house in the center left appears to have piles of granite rubble or rocks to the left and behind it. Another building is seen on the edge of the pond in the center distance. Most of the image consists of pond and open ground. Original photograph by the Draper Company. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 5, Item 1019 for print of this negative.
  - Dr. G. N. Hatch residence on west side of Hopedale Street (Box 2, Folder 1020)
    Negative no.A1020. 1891-1895. Image depicts a two-story wooden house with two chimneys and shutters at each window. A bay window and small porch face the unpaved street; two people can be seen on the porch, a man and a woman. A second porch is on the side of the house. See also Negative 1021, in this box, which shows the same house and people, although they are standing on the side porch and somewhat more visible. Original photograph by the Draper Company. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 5, Item 1020 for print of this negative.
  - Hopedale, Massachusetts: Dr. G. N. Hatch residence on west side of Hopedale Street (Box 2, Folder 1021)
    Negative no.A1021. 1891-1895. Image depicts a two-story wooden house with two chimneys and shutters at each window. A bay window and small porch face the unpaved street; a second porch is on the side of the house where an elderly man and woman are standing. See also Negative 1020, in this box, which shows the same house and people, although they are somewhat hidden on the front porch. Original photograph by the Draper Company. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 5, Item 1021 for print of this negative.
  - Draper Company: set of screw samples (Box 2, Folder 1022)
    Negative no.A1022. 1891-1895. Image depicts a framed set of screw samples, each labeled with a number. They range in size from quite thin and small to very thick. Draper apparently manufactured their own screws in their machine screw shop. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 6, Item 1022 for print of this negative.
  - Hopedale, Massachusetts: Mrs. Southwick's house on Freedom Street (Box 2, Folder 1023)
    Negative no.A1023. 1891-1895. Image depicts two-story wooden home with gabled roof, three chimneys, and shutters at each window. The front porch is covered with ivy, as is a small portion of the side of the house. A sidewalk runs between the house and the unpaved street. Another home is partially visible on the right. It is not known who Mrs. Southwick was. Original photograph by the Draper Company. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 6, Item 1023 for print of this negative.
  - Hopedale, Massachusetts: spindle & rink factory (Box 2, Folder 1024)
    Negative no.A1024. 1891-1895. Image depicts the spindle & rink factory at center right, showing a complex of three-story brick buildings with three chimneys in a row on the left, behind which is a taller chimney. A covered walkway slopes down on the left to a smaller building on the far left. The view looks north with the river and rural surroundings in background. The spindle factory, built in 1881, was the business known as A.A. Westcott & Sons. It was located in a section of Hopedale known as Spindleville, after the factory. Original photograph by the Draper Company. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 6, Item 1024 for print of this negative.
  - Rows of Equipment (Box 2, Folder 1025)
    Negative no.A1025. 1891-1895. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 6, Item 1025 for print of this negative.
  - Hopedale, Massachusetts: aerial view looking southeast along Hopedale Street (Box 2, Folder 1026)
    Negative no.A1026. 1891-1895. Image depicts an aerial view, possibly taken from a Draper Co. chimney, of business and residential buildings lining several town streets. Not the same view seen in Box 3, Negative 1044. Original photograph by the Draper Company. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 6, Item 1026 for print of this negative.
  - Pattern Room, Draper Company (Box 2, Folder 1027)
    Negative no.A1027. 1891-1895. Image depicts the pattern room, also called the pattern shop, at Draper Company. Here is where wooden patterns of gears and parts would be made before the parts would be manufactured in metal form. Six male workers are visible, standing around the shop. Several tables are laid out in a line down the room and carpenters' tools can be seen on the shelves in the right background. More tools are on the counters under the windows on the right. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. See Box 1, Negative 1009 for another view of this room with some of the same employees. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 6, Item 1027 for print of this negative.
  - Wrecked chimney, Draper Company (Box 2, Folder 1028)